with physicality comes the physiological
and no other endeavor puts the human
body to the test quite like MMA but
beyond the bones and muscle lie the
building blocks of life and 1 Cal State
Fullerton professor is finding some
interesting things about the DNA of a
fighter
I'm a professor of human performance and
muscle physiology at the Center for
sport performance in California State
University Fullerton so my role is to
test these guys in methods that they
can't do outside of our lab setting
90-degree angle and let it flop down to
there today we're gonna take them
through a full gamut of testing we're
gonna look at their vertical jump
performance we're gonna look at their
other aspects of their power so what
we're gonna have him do is pull up on
that bar as hard and as fast as he
possibly can and we'll know how much
force he actually produces in the ground
and more importantly we'll know how fast
he produces that force we know unlike a
sport of MMA being strong is important
but you've only got a limited amount of
time to actually implement that force
once I started understanding MMA a
little bit more I became really curious
in the actual physiology behind it
because it doesn't fit anywhere in our
normal spectrum of anaerobic power
sports or aerobic endurance sports so
now we want to put tom through a test of
'he's an aerobic power this is standard
to a typical Wingate test but we're
gonna actually tweak it a little bit to
make it much more specific to what
actually Tom does in his MMA fight
I'm okay
another test we like to do here is
actually a measure of grip strength this
is particularly important for somebody
like Pat who likes to use a lot of
grappling in his fighting good and
excellent so that's gonna give us a
feedback I don't know if I should show
you this or not this is Oh not his best
performance at the end of that we're
actually gonna go in and take a muscle
biopsy so we can pull out the muscle and
start to analyze it it's a single fiber
level reach in with the right tweezer
just simply pull out fibers one by one
you can see that's one individual fiber
right there what we're looking at here
is the actual distribution of their
muscle fiber type so each one of these
black dots is a lane which represents an
individual one of their muscle fibers so
now we simply have to count how many of
these fast fibers they have versus how
many slow and how many of them are in
this hybrid form what we're actually
seeing in our lab is that there's
something different at the level of the
DNA at the level of the individual cell
with these fighters something at the
cellular level differentiates them from
elite football players basketball
players or anything else
so what we're trying to do is explore
that figure out how are they doing these
things that we thought couldn't be done
straight from the lab to the studio we
welcome in dr. Andy Galpin welcome to
inside MMA thanks guys pleasure to be
here but a longtime fan I appreciate
that you talking about it in the back
this is a fascinating study that you
guys are doing you see you going in and
checking out the DNA and the fibers of
these fighters so how does the DNA of a
mixed martial artist differ from other
athletes or just from other people
well we actually had no idea this was
happening until we started looking so we
started taking biopsies of these UFC
fighters and other MMA fighters started
realizing something's different about
their muscle so as an example every
individual human muscle fiber like he
saw in the image there has thousands of
nuclei the nuclei are what control the
cell and what hold the DNA and so I
originally started with this question
when I started think
how is it that these MMA fighters can
recover so well from all the training
that they're doing right well that
recovery and the adaptability and the
recovery of a muscle cell comes from the
nucleus so when we started taking a look
at some of these athletes we started
seeing wow they've gotten more nuclei
and they've got different nuclei they're
in different portions of the cell and so
we started literally thinking you guys
have seen that t-shirt
Fighting's in my DNA right yeah oh my
gosh
something is different way they regulate
their muscle the way they recover the
way they train again perhaps the way
they're able to to grow and adapt is
it's different from them from any other
non athlete and from any other high
level athlete that we've ever seen
before
maybe adrenaline junkies tried to find
those guys those like skateboarders or
something crazy stuff maybe that's the
same I had a question about the fast
rich and the slow twitch fibers because
I always thought that the fast rates
fibers if you have explosiveness that
you take burn way more and that you need
way more oxygen then slow twitch but you
say that's not the case some people have
both you know we used to think the same
thing actually so the way that it works
is all of your muscle for the most part
is split it has some portion of one
muscle is a little bit fast and some
portion of it is slow some people have a
higher percentage of fast in that muscle
some have a higher percentage of slope
traditionally we think the people that
have a higher percentage of fast or more
explosive and get tired quicker that as
you mentioned yo we're actually seeing
with these UFC fighters is that's not
true yeah I take Patrick Cummins perfect
example and he's the one that's actually
jumped out at me he is a conditioning
type of guy he's an endurance type of
guy he's a grinding wrestler right known
to never get tired he's huge on the fast
twitch spectrum he's way higher in fact
than almost anybody we've ever seen and
this is actually when it first jumped
out to me we just started thinking like
this is not making sense yeah something
is different physiologically about these
elite level MMA fighters that we didn't
really appreciate scientifically yep
Andy at the end of the day what is the
ultimate goal of this research study and
what are some of the next steps yeah so
it's really twofold number one I work in
the center for sport performance so we
want to do research that helps sport
performance so first and foremost I want
to give these guys
and girls any information I can to
actually help their performance so
trying to keep them as healthy as
humanly possible reduce the injury stuff
and maximize her performance
it works out conveniently for me because
I'm also interested in actually learning
more about human physiology and as we
kind of mentioned earlier we're finding
things about them we've never seen in
any other human so we're learning a lot
about muscle physiology from these
people so what kind of works both ways I
learn a lot and they get something out
of it too
okay real fast what's the craziest thing
you ever did in the lab that you sorted
okay this is out of control
I would like to be honest now I would
have to say the first time we did the
fiber typing and we started to figure
out what percentage of fiber types these
guys have and when we started realizing
they're way off the charts yeah and so
we did it again and again I'm gonna go
by I'm gonna donate some fibers I want
to see what's going on to see it ah
please that would explain so much break
some reason to break any excuse to take
a needle in his leg I'll take it inside
MMA live every Friday night on access TV
your home for MMA